So today's דף daf is מט Mem Tet and we start on
מח Mem Chet עמוד ב'. amud bet. We are right in the
middle of the page. תנו רבנן כל הנבדקות. Tano banan kol hanivdakot.
Line starts with the word נבדקות. nivdakot. It's literally the exact middle
of the page. So we talked about the signs of puberty, of
adulthood, two pubic hairs, and upper signs, lower signs, and now we're
going to talk about who does the checking. תנו רבנן כל הנבדקות
נבדקות על פי נשים. Tano banan kol hanivdakot nivdakot al pi nashim.
All the girls that are checked are checked on the basis of
women's testimony, you have women check. וכן היה רבי אליעזר מוסר לאשתו,
V'chen haya Rabbi Eliezer moseir l'ishto, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would give
it over to his wife to check if there was a הלכה
halakha issue that needed about a question about whether a girl was
an adult or not. מיאון, miun, חליצה, chalitza, the issues we've been
discussing.
רבי ישמעאל מוסר לאמו, Rabbi Yishmael moseir l'imo, רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
would have his mother check. רבי יהודה אומר מפני הפרק ולאחר הפרק
נשים בודקות אותן. Rabbi Yehuda Omer: Mifnei haperek ul'achar haperek nashim bodkot
otan. Before the time and after the time then you can have
women check them. תוך הפרק אין נשים בודקות אותן. Toch haperek ein
nashim bodkot otan. During this time you can't have women check them,
שאין משיאין ספקות על פי נשים. she'ein masi'in sefeikot al pi nashim.
You do not allow the doubts to be determined by women. Now
obviously the question is what's before, during, and after? So as the
גמרא Gemara will say, after is after twelve and a day, before
is before eleven and a day, and the time where it's less
clear is between the twelfth year, eleven and a day and twelve
and a day. Of course the question is who cares at that
time, the hairs don't mean anything? So we'll see about all of
that in a minute, but obviously the principle is clear and the
principle is that
when it's either moot or pretty obvious what the story is and
you don't really need the women's testimony, before the time, after the
time, then you can rely on it. When there's a real issue
of a doubt and the testimony is really necessary, you cannot. And
we will see a number of opinions that are about to follow
about not using women's testimony, and we'll discuss and what the הלכה
halakha is. But let me just say right now there's obviously two
ways of understanding what the hesitancy is about trusting the women's testimony.
One is just generally not trusting women, maybe not necessarily that they
would lie but let's say lack of accuracy or something. Of course
it's pretty funny given that the גמרא Gemara has not yet really
set too many criteria about what constitutes
a is there like something that is a good hair, something that
doesn't really count as a good hair. It's not like it requires
any particular expertise. I mean we'll see a little bit later that
maybe it has to be a certain length, but it's hard to
imagine that there's a real question here
about whether women could be believed. It seems more that it's a
question, it's a formal question because here if you're testifying that somebody's
an adult, to what degree is that considered to be classic testimony
and classic testimony is by men? And to what degree is it
considered more
like sort of testifying that something is כשר kosher or not like
עד אחד נאמן באיסורין eid echad ne'eman b'issurin where it also can
be by women? Like you notice by the way that the גמרא
Gemara never spoke about the question about whether you need to have
two, right? It says he gave to his wife, he gave to
his mother, so it doesn't sound like this is a case of
classic testimony which could mean that women are okay. It's just about
being believed and assessing facts and so on. So the position that
you don't trust women might be based on or you don't rely
on women I should say, that would be seen as a case
of like formal testimony that requires two men.
However, it's not explicit from the גמרא Gemara that way and who
knows maybe it is a question about believability, but in other cases
like כשרות kashrut we have no problem relying on women, so I'm
more inclined to think it's a formal question. Okay so that's the
position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that when there's a real doubt
you cannot use women's testimony. רבי שמעון אומר אף תוך הפרק נשים
בודקות אותן. Rabbi Shimon Omer: Af toch haperek nashim bodkot otan. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says
even during this time which is this doubtful time women can check.
ונאמנת אשה להחמיר ולא להקל. V'ne'emenet isha l'hachmir v'lo l'hakel.
But then he seems to take away with his right what he
gave with his left
which he says
yeah but even though we trust them it's only to be strict,
not to be lenient, which also seems to suggest that we really
cannot rely on them. So we'll have to see what the difference
is of this position with רבי יהודה'ס. Rabbi Yehuda's. כיצד? Keitzad? Now
we're going to spell it out. גדולה היא, Gdola hi,
what does it mean this is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon talking that
we can be strict and not lenient?
If they say she's an adult then we would say okay we
believe that to the effect שלא תמאן, shelo temaein, we don't let
her do מיאון. miun. מיאון miun is only doable by minors. We
don't allow her to do חליצה, chalitza, but at the same time
we prevent her from doing מיאון. miun. So we're strict, we accept
that testimony to be strict שלא תמאן. shelo temaein. קטנה היא, Ktana
hi,
let's say they say she's a minor, so we say fine we'll
accept that שלא תחלוץ, shelo tachlotz, not to let her do חליצה.
chalitza. So we'll accept the testimony to be strict but not to
be lenient. אבל אין נאמנת לומר קטנה היא שתמאן, Aval ein ne'emenet
lomar ktana hi she'temaein, if they were to say that she's a
minor then we would not accept that to be lenient to allow
her to do something, to allow her to do מיאון. miun. וגדולה
היא, U'gedola hi, we don't accept the testimony that she's an adult
שתחלוץ she'tachlotz or she's to do חליצה. chalitza. Okay so that's very
clear, we take it to be strict. Now the key question here
though is how's that different than רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda? basically says
we don't rely on them for doubts? Where's the line of difference?
Both of them don't really rely on it. And the other question
is, what is this middle time as opposed to earlier and later?
So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says.
Yes, so
remember earlier when we were talking about showing the blood, you remember
there's that חיותא hayuta שאינה she'eino מדברת, medaberet, where we see it
before her blood, we don't see that anyone would disagree with it
over here, so now we see...
Right,
so that's what I... so I didn't spell it out, but that's
what I was getting at, which is that,
questions about איסור issur like 'are you a נדה, niddah, you're not
a נדה', niddah 'is the food in the house כשר', kosher there
that's basically עד ed אחד echad נאמן ne'eman באיסורין, b'issurin, women are
believed absolutely no question. One of the sources of עד ed אחד
echad נאמן ne'eman באיסורין b'issurin could be the exact הלכה halacha of
נדה. niddah. But here it's different, here it's an issue about personal
status. And personal status is not necessarily 'is this כשר kosher or
טרף, treif, אסור assur or forbidden', it's personal status, and therefore that
might more be like אין ein דבר davar שבערוה she'be'erva פחות pachot
משנים, mishnayim, is a person liable for being punished in the court,
those are types of issues that might really require real testimony. So
that might be part of the issue. And the reason you according
to the opinions that you do rely on less than on maybe
on one witness or on women might be not that they disagree
that this is a fundamentally an issue of עדות edut or of
testimony, but that might be because it's what's called עבידא avidah לגלויי,
l'igluyei, that it's something that is easily determinable, and therefore it's considered
like you don't need that lowers the standard of proof needed. But
that's exactly this question of whether it is similar to an issue
of איסור issur or whether it's more of a personal status and
requires עדות, edut, that could be exact the question.
נדה Niddah is still a personal status
and she's נדה niddah or she's not, right? It's both איסור issur
and personal... if she's not נדה niddah she's based on the showing
of the blood and the husband and wife says...
I know, but that's not personal status. That's fundamentally a question of
like of 'are you, it's more are you forbidden or permissible', it's
not a which is a classic איסור issur question. If a person
is an adult, it has it's not permissible, it has profound implications.
Can they enter into transactions? What are the what's the meaning of
this act? What that's a thing which is much much more profound
than the question about is this כשר kosher or כשר kosher or
טרף, treif, מותר mutar or אסור. assur. So that's the much more
the could be the category of אין ein דבר davar שבערוה she'be'erva
פחות pachot משנים. mishnayim. Okay, that's the issue of defining the line
between when do you need עדות edut and when do you need
נאמנות. ne'emanus. All right, so let's continue. Let's see where the גמרא
Gemara goes. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמר Amar מר,
mar, רבי יהודה אומר: Rebbi Yehuda omer, לפני lifnei הפרק ha'perek ולאחר
v'achar הפרק ha'perek נשים בודקות אותן. nashim bodkos osan
Before and after, yes you can use women. So what's before and
after? So let's take a look. בשלמא Bishlama לפני lifnei הפרק ha'perek
בעי ba'ei בדיקה bdika דאי d'im משתכחי mishtakei לאחר l'achar הפרק ha'perek
שומא נינהו. shuma ninhu
If you check why would you need to check beforehand anyway? Because
I mean if beforehand means when she's like under 11, I mean
under 11 and a day, then who cares even if she does
have hair, it's meaningless. So the גמרא Gemara says though actually there
is a case where it is meaningless the where it's meaningful. The
where it's meaningful is
that
you find a hair. And remember we said that if hairs grow
before the age, the right age, then even if they're there when
you hit the right age, they're not meaningful, because it's שומא, shuma
like it grew from a mole or something. So therefore the checking
will have significance. If they check now, then they can say: 'Yeah,
that hair was there from before, and therefore later you'll want to
assume that she's an adult, and they you will say she's not
an adult based on the checking that they did prior'. Okay, so
that would be meaningful. That we get.
Let's take a look. בשלמא Bishlama לזה l'zeh בעי ba'ei בדיקה bdika
דאי d'im משתכחי mishtakei לאחר l'achar הפרק ha'perek
if you find it afterwards שומא shuma, נינהו, ninhu. you'll discount it
because you'll say 'Oh yeah, that was there from before, we know
because women checked and saw it'. אלא Ela לאחר achar הפרק ha'perek
למה lama לי li בדיקה? bdika? What's the point of checking after
the פרק? perek? Because the גמרא Gemara somehow assumes that, well we'll
see the answer, but presumably it means that we could assume that
maybe there will be hair. Let's take a look.
So the גמרא Gemara says: למה Lama לי li בדיקה? bdika? ואמר
V'amar רבא: Rava: קטנה ktana שהגיעה she'higia לכלל l'klal שנותיה shnoteha אינה
eina צריכה tzricha בדיקה, bdika, חזקה chazaka היא hi שהביאה she'hevi'a סימנים,
simanim,
like we said yesterday, the חזקה chazaka of רבא. Rava. Once you
come of the right age, you don't need to check, we can
assume that you've had the hairs. So the גמרא Gemara says like
it said the other day that the חזקה chazaka of רבא Rava
is not 100%, is not always applied. לא, No, כי ki אמר
amar רבא Rava חזקה chazaka למיאון. l'miun. רבא Rava only said we
can rely on that for מיאון, miun, meaning again essentially to be
strict, or if you want for rabbinic purposes. Because if you assume
she has hairs, then she's an adult and she cannot do מיאון.
miun. So to be strict or for rabbinic purposes, we rely on
רבא'ס Rava's חזקה. chazaka. אבל Aval לחליצה, l'chalitza, to assume that she
has hairs for חליצה, chalitza, which is A: to be lenient, meaning
to allow her to do something, and B: for דאורייתא d'oraisa purpose,
בעי ba'ei בדיקה, bdika, you would not
rely on
רבא'ס Rava's חזקה. chazaka. Okay, so. You know it's something that maybe
requires real testimony you don't rely you don't use women's testimony beforehand
I'm sorry wait a minute excuse me excuse me I misstated that
after I misstated that afterward excuse me afterward you can't go just
on חזקה דרבה Chazaka deRabba excuse me but because you do have
חזקה דרבה Chazaka deRabba the argument seems to be when it's combined
with this testimony the testimony of women then it will work. So
afterward it will work because at least it has חזקה דרבה Chazaka
deRabba to back it up. Okay but during this time where it
doesn't have חזקה דרבה Chazaka deRabba then you can't. So let's take
a look at what during this time means. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this תוך הפרק אין נשים בודקות אותן toch haperak ein
nashim bodkos osan during this period you cannot have women check. קסבר
kasavar so first of all who cares during this period if it's
the 12th year even if she has two hairs it's irrelevant so
why would I need women to check why should I care? So
what what's the meaning of that? So קסבר תוך הפרק כלאחר הפרק.
kasavar toch haperak k'le-achar haperak. No so the only way this is
this would be we would care about checking during the the 12th
year is if you say that during the 12th year with two
hairs she actually is considered an adult. ולאחר ve-le-achar so now what
is the difference then why can you rely on the checking done
after 12 and a day and not done during the 12th year
if in both times the two hairs make her an adult for
the following reason? לאחר הפרק דאיכא חזקה דרבה le-achar haperak de-ika chazaka
deRabba
after 12 years and a day where you have the חזקה דרבה
chazaka deRabba that would allow you to assume anyway probably there are
hairs regardless so therefore סמכינן א-נשים somchinan a-nashim you don't go you
don't use Rabba's חזקה chazaka all the way you don't use it
to be lenient or for דאורייתא de-Oraisa but if you combine it
with the testimony of women then therefore you can rely on it.
So afterward you have the reinforcing of the חזקה דרבה chazaka deRabba
you can rely on it. ובדקי u-vadki they can check. תוך הפרק
דליכא חזקה דרבה toch haperak de-leika chazaka deRabba the year before the
12th year although if you were to have hairs she would be
an adult but there it's much more doubtful whether she has hairs
there's a real ספק safek so during that period where there's a
real ספק safek and nothing to reinforce it תוך הפרק דליכא חזקה
דרבה לא סמכינן א-נשים ולא בדקי נשים toch haperak de-leika chazaka deRabba
lo somchinan a-nashim ve-lo bodki nashim
we do not rely on women and the women cannot check. א-נשים
a-nashim means on women not אנשים anashim men. Okay so therefore basically
what this is saying is it's not now we see how it's
different than רבי שמעון's Rebbi Shimon's position. It's saying you know what
sometimes we will rely on women's testimony to be not to be
lenient it's not just we'll strict and not lenient but you need
something reinforcing it. If it's a question of a real doubt like
during that 12th year you will not use testimony of women by
itself. If it's reinforced with חזקה דרבה chazaka deRabba then you will
use it whether to be lenient or whether
to
be
strict that is the position of רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda that
with reinforcing evidence we'll rely on it. Now let's take a look
at what רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon says.
Okay רבי שמעון אומר אף תוך הפרק Rebbi Shimon omer af toch
haperak even during this period the 12th year נשים בודקות אותן nashim
bodkos osan you can rely on women but we're going about to
find out that that's only to be strict anyway so it doesn't
really mean rely anyway. נשים nashim בודקות bodkot אותן otan. so גמרא
Gemara says קסבר תוך הפרק כלפני הפרק ובעי בדיקה. kasavar toch haperak
k'lifnei haperak ve-baei bedika.
So he says first of all what does it mean you can
rely on them since we know he's only going to be strict
so it doesn't really mean rely on them? It means that anyway
the 12th year is like the 11th year so even if there
are two
hairs it's not going to be considered her an adult. So why
are you bothering checking? ובעי בדיקה u-baei bedika why do you bother
checking? דאי משכחי לאחר הפרק de-ee mashkechi le-achar haperak because then if
you find the hairs afterward those same hairs that were identified earlier
then שומא shuma נינהו ninhu, then we'll say oh she's not really
an adult maybe those are you know from a mole because we
saw that the hairs were there from before. So when he says
you can check during how is that consistent with the idea of
being only being strict because checking during during is considered prior it's
considered like it won't make her an adult and the checking will
only allow you to be strict? You check and you see hairs
that means that when you want to call her an adult
later you will have reservations about that and you'll be strict because
of the testimony from before. So that's רבי שמעון Rebbi Shimon that
says we're only going to be strict. And now let's continue. ונאמנת
אשה להחמיר ולא להקל ve-ne'emenes isha lehachmir ve-lo lehakeil and you can
be strict and not lenient. היי מאן קתני לה hai man katni
lah who is this going by? אי בעית אימא רבי יהודה ואתוך
הפרק ee ba-is eima Rebbi Yehuda ve-a'toch haperak either it's רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda and it's during the period. During this time, right? During
the 12th year for Rebbi Yehuda, you do not accept women's testimony
because it does not have the reinforcing חזקה chazakah of Rabbah. So
during that year, you will at least accept it to be stringent,
meaning like you won't let her do מיאון, miun, right? Remember Rebbi
Yehuda says during that year is like after the year, so if
they have hairs during that year, according to Rebbi Yehuda that would
make these girls adult. So according to him, you will accept that
testimony for the purposes of being strict. איבעית אימא Ibe'is eima Rebbi
Shimon, or maybe it's Rebbi Shimon, ולאחר פרק, u'l'achar perek, and he
and he would say that even when they testify after twelve years
and a day, you would not accept the testimony of women. Why
not? לית ליה חזקה דרבא. Leis lei chazakah d'Rabba. Now, could have
said that even with חזקה דרבא chazakah d'Rabba he doesn't care, he
never accepts women's testimony even with חזקה דרבא chazakah d'Rabba reinforcing it,
but the גמרא Gemara doesn't say that. It says really, basically, it's
what the גמרא Gemara is saying is Rebbi Yehuda and Rebbi Shimon
fundamentally say the same thing. You don't accept women's testimony on its
own to be lenient, you accept it to be strict. And then
the only debates are how they hold about different time periods. So
Rebbi Yehuda holds that the 12th year is like it's already afterwards,
so therefore that leads to his start of saying certain things. Rebbi
Shimon holds the 12th year is before, and now this other question
of can you also use the חזקה דרבא. chazakah d'Rabba. So if
you so if you believe in the חזקה דרבא chazakah d'Rabba you
can use it to reinforce and rely on women's testimony, and if
you don't believe in the חזקה דרבא chazakah d'Rabba you cannot use
it and therefore you cannot accept women's testimony. So according to the
last two opinions, again, they both agree, the first opinion says of
course you rely on women, the next two opinions says no fundamentally
you do not, you will use their testimony to be strict. What's
an example of being strict? Number one, if they say there's hairs
when they were minors, then you will have to consider you will
you will have to be strict about that that if there's the
same hairs when they are twelve and a day you cannot assume
they're adults because you have to be strict based on the testimony
of women. The other case that you have to be strict is
you know is during the 12th during if you assume that during
the 12th year she's considered to be during the 12th year's after
like 12 years and a day, then you're strict that if they
say that they've hairs you consider an adult, you don't let her
do מיאון, miun, it's strict in that you don't allow her to
do what a קטנה ketanah would do, but you're not lenient. And
after 12 years and a day, then there's a debate if you
can if you use חזקה דרבא chazakah d'Rabba then finally you can
actually rely on the women's testimony to give her a full status
of an adult. If you don't use חזקה דרבא chazakah d'Rabba then
you're like you were before, you can't use the woman's testimony, you
can't assume she's an adult, you can only assume it for the
purposes of being strict, not for the purposes of being lenient. So
these are the positions of Rebbi Yehuda and Rebbi Shimon, very similar
in that you're strict and not lenient, and the only question is
is that do you hold of the חזקה chazakah of Rabbah. Now,
how do we פסקן? pasken? If you look at the end of
this big תוספות Tosafot איבעית אימא ibe'is eima near the bottom, תוספות
Tosafot says like this, he says
one
minute, he says like this. And
is he even suggesting that they should be checked for these reasons?
So
תוספות Tosafot has that question too, when it says you check before
the פרק, perek, does it really mean you have to? In order
to he's basically says no, no, no, it doesn't mean you have
to, although the גמרא Gemara sounds like that a little bit. Nobody
says you have to, but תוספות Tosafot basically rejects that read. Anyway,
I just want to find you the line of תוספות Tosafot where
he says what we do. He says like this,
yeah, he does say like לכתחילה lechatchila maybe it would be a
good idea to check beforehand but not that you're really required.
Somewhere he says he's just trying to find it that the מנהג
minhag is, the רמב"ם Rambam פסקן pasken straight out that we rely
on women, presumably פסקן pasken like the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, and
תוספות Tosafot says here, let me just try to find it, hold
on,
yeah, so if you take a look about six lines before the
lines get wide where the line starts with the word איירי, airi,
תוספות Tosafot says ומעשים בכל יום דסמכינן אבדיקת נשים לאחר הפרק והיינו
דלא כרבי שמעון ואפילו בתוך הפרק לפני הפרק אמר רבי דאין הלכה
כרבי שמעון
u'ma'asim b'chol yom d'samchinan a'bedikas nashim l'achar haperek v'hainu d'lo k'Rebbi Shimon
v'afilu b'soch haperek lifnei
haperek amar Rebbi d'ein halacha k'Rebbi Shimon etc. etc.
So תוספות Tosafot basically says yeah of course we rely on women
for this, we do not have men doing the checking. The reason
might be because we rule like חזקה דרבא, chazakah d'Rabba, so therefore
the checking afterwards can be relied on to to assume she's an
adult based on the reinforcing of חזקה דרבא. chazakah d'Rabba. So we
do rely on women, it's not clear whether we rely on it
because fundamentally we rely on it like the first position, or whether
we rely on it because of we rely on it once she's
already once it's after 12 years and a day based on חזקה
דרבא, chazakah d'Rabba, but that is the conclusion both of תוספות Tosafot
and of the רמב"ם Rambam that we rely on the checking of
women. Okay so now let's just finish up to the משנה, Mishnah,
back to the גמרא, Gemara, let's just finish to the משנה. Mishnah.
Yeah.
Is that for all the stories we've discussed?
Well, no, you mean if according to according to the first opinion
you would trust women whether to be lenient or to be strict,
whether after twelve and a day or earlier, but according to the
second opinion the
תוספות's Tosafot way, we rely on women just because. It's the reinforcing
of חזקה דרבא, Chazaka d'Rava, so according to that, you would only
rely on women's testimony to be lenient when it was the issue
of the two pubic hairs after twelve and a day. For other
purposes you would not rely on it. So there's a big difference
which of these two approaches you take. You're right. If it was
for the other time periods, either before twelve and a day or
for these other stages, three and a day, those other types of—that's
not about pubic hairs, but whatever—anyway, for these other possible stages, it
would not be to rely on—it depends which position, whether it's based
on חזקה דרבא Chazaka d'Rava or whether it's independently you rely on
women.
That is correct.
Okay, so let's take a look now to the משנה. Mishna. ממאי
אמרו אפשר, Mimai amru efshar,
so the משנה Mishna ends and says so, you remember the משנה
Mishna said,
it's impossible for the top סימן Siman to come before the lower
one and then it said, so then it just—it said that at
the beginning and it reinforced it at the end. So the גמרא
Gemara says, הא תו למה לי, Ha tu lama li, after you
said it's impossible, why do you have to at the end say
because it's impossible for the top סימן Siman before the bottom one?
So דתנא לה רישא, Detana lah reisha, it said in the beginning.
וכי תימא משום דקבעי למסתמא כרבנן, Vechai teima mishum dekabei lemistama kerabanan,
because you want to just say the anonymous voice like the רבנן
Rabbanan that the top סימן Siman does not become before the bottom
one? פשיטא, Pshita, obviously, יחיד ורבים הלכה כרבים, Yachid verabbim halacha kerabbim,
you know, if it's a minority against a majority we go by
the majority. So the גמרא Gemara says no, מהו דתימא מסתברא טעמיה
דרבי מאיר, Mahu deteima mistabra taameih deRabbi Meir, I might have thought
that רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir idea that sometimes the upper סימן Siman
could come first makes sense. Why? דקמסייע ליה קראי, Dekamsayeia leih kray,
because the פסוקים Psukim support it. קא משמע לן, Ka mashma lan,
so this teaches you that nevertheless we rule like the רבנן. Rabbanan.
ואיבעית אימא, Ve'iba'is eima, and if you want I could say it's
not really needed for הלכה Halacha purposes, but for sort of like
a literary purpose, משום דקבעי למתני כיוצא בו, Mishum dekabei lemasnei kiyotzei
bo, because we want to have the next משנה Mishna כיוצא בו,
Kiyotzei bo, which draws a similarity, so we want to set up—as
you're going to see, this is one of the many times where
the משניות Mishnayos use a certain sort of structural similarity to bring
in randomly different or very widely different cases because there's a structural
similarity. So that's what we're doing, we're sort of setting it up
for the next משנה. Mishna. And the setup is: you can have
A without B, but you can't have B without A. You can
have pubic hairs without the סימן עליון Siman elyon without the breast
development, but you can't have the סימן עליון Siman elyon without the
סימן תחתון. Siman tachton. So it ended that way in order to
set up the next משנה Mishna and then—now we're going to—that's a
perfect segue, we're going to look at a couple of משניות Mishnayos
for the next few days that are going to have nothing to
do with נדה Niddah but are about: you can have A without
B but you can't have B without A. Okay, so let's take
a look. Next משנה. Mishna. Now something—now for something completely different. All
right, so here's what the משנה Mishna says. כיוצא בו, Kiyotzei bo,
similarly, כל כלי חרס שמכניס מוציא, Kol kli cheres shemachnis motzi,
any pottery vessel that water can come in, water will go out.
ויש שמוציא ואינו מכניס, Veyeish shemotzi ve'eino machnis, some have water go
out not come in. Now this is talking about if you have
pottery vessels with a little hole on the bottom, that hole for
various purposes can make it considered to be not a vessel. How
big does that hole have to be? So there are two ways
of defining—two different—well, there's multiple types of holes, but the smallest two
is one, a hole small enough—it's small but it's still big enough
that water—if there's water in the vessel, the water will go out.
And then the next size larger is that it's big enough that
water outside of the vessel will come in. The obvious difference is
that the reason the first one can be smaller is because you
have the water pressure inside of the vessel pushing down on the
hole. So even if it's a smaller hole, it's easier for water
to go out of the hole than it is for water to
go in. So you have those types of things that if it's
big enough for water to go in, then it's big enough water
to go out, but it sometimes—but it can be—but if it's the
size that water goes out, water will not necessarily go in. כל
אבר שיש בו צפורן יש בו עצם. Kol eiver sheyeish bo tziporen
yeish bo etzem. If you have a limb—this is talking about a
person that has an extra, let's say, finger, a digit on his
body—and is that considered to be an אבר Eiver for the purposes
of if it falls off of the body, is it אבר מן
החי Eiver min hachai that it causes טומאה? Tumah? Or if it's
separated from the body after death, is it אבר מן המת? Eiver
min hamet? And an אבר Eiver of—and the only type of thing
that causes טומאה Tumah from a living body is an אבר מן
החי. Eiver min hachai. And even from a dead body, although anything
causes טומאה, Tumah, the only amount—you need a certain minimum amount, but
especially to cause טומאה Tumah in a tent. But if it's an
entire limb, then even without a minimum amount. So what is considered
to be a limb? So in those cases when you're dealing with
an extra digit, it's only considered to be a limb if it
has both bone and nail. Inside a bone and a fingernail or
a toenail. Okay, that's for extra digits. For the primary digits even
without that, but for extra digits only with both of those. So
it says, כל אבר שיש בו צפורן יש בו עצם, Kol eiver
sheyeish bo tziporen yeish bo etzem, every digit that has a nail,
fingernail, will also have a bone. ויש שיש בו עצם ואין בו
צפורן, Veyeish sheyeish bo etzem ve'ein bo tziporen, some will have a
bone but not have a fingernail. And therefore it will not have
the הלכה Halacha of an אבר. Eiver. כל המטמא מדרס מטמא טמא
מת, Kol hametamei midras metamei tamei met, any type of a כלי
Kli that can become טמא Tamei because of a זב Zav and
a זבה Zava sitting on it, right, which is מדרס, Midras, a
seat, can become טמא Tamei by a contact with a dead body.
The reason—the reason we gave the example of a dead body is
both of these are אב הטומאה. Av hatumah. If a זב Zav
or זבה Zava sits on a seat, it becomes an אב, Av,
not a ראשון. Rishon. And if a dead body touches something, something
touches a dead body, it becomes an אב, Av, not a ראשון.
Rishon. So anything that's a seat is also considered a vessel to
receive טומאה Tumah from a dead body. the ויש שמטמא טמא מת
ואינו מטמא מדרס: v'yeish shemetamei tamei meis v'eino metamei midras:
something can become טמא tamei from a dead body but would not
be considered a seat and therefore could not be considered and therefore
it can be one without the other, it can be טמא tamei
for a dead body not a seat. And the גמרא Gemorah will
give an interesting example, but the obvious example would be, let's say
you have a pin, right? If you touch a pin, a little
metal vessel, tiny metal vessel to a dead body, it becomes טמא,
tamei, it's an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. But obviously if a זב
zav or זבה zavah sits on it, it's not a seat. So
you have something that can be טמא tamei that way without being
the טומאה tumah of a זב zav and a זבה. zavah. Okay,
so now let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemorah. מכניס פסול
למי חטאת, machnis pasul l'mei chatas, if
it water can come in, then it is invalid for using it
for the vessel for
for sprinkling the ashes of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, right? You
in order to mix the ashes of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah,
you have to put the live water, the water from the wellspring
and the ashes into a vessel. So there it has to be,
in order to be a vessel for that purposes, it cannot have
a hole big enough in order for the water to come in.
But ופסול משום גיסטרא. u'pasul mishum gistera. Let's say you have a
pottery shard. If you have a pottery shard, normally of course that
wouldn't be a vessel. But let's say you designated it for a
vessel, your pot broke, and you still have a curved part of
the pot that you can put down and it'll be stable on
a table, and you could put a little oil in it and
use it for to you know to dip your bread into, you
put a little oil in that. If you designated it as that,
that counts as a vessel. Okay, but because of course it is
a very you know iffy type of a vessel, it's much easier
for it to lose its status. So even a whole even a
whole
that's the size of so excuse me, so a hole the size
here of that water can come in makes this pottery shard lose
its status. This will be clear when we look at what this
contrasts to. Let's look at the next case: מוציא, motzi, however let's
say the hole is smaller, water can't come in but water will
only go out. In that case of course, it does not affect
the status of the vessels as much. כשר למי חטאת, kasher l'mei
chatas, so if you have a pottery vessel that has a hole
only tiny enough that water can go out but not in, it's
still considered a vessel for the purposes of a
פרה אדומה. parah adumah. So really it does not affect the status
of a vessel. But one type of case where it affects the
status of a vessel, this tiny hole, is פוסל משום גיסטרא. posel
mishum gistera.
If you have something that's only a little shard, which is barely
a vessel to begin with, in that type of a case this
tiny hole will invalidate it. So what's the basic rule? A hole
the size enough for water to go in invalidates vessels more across
the board, if it's so tiny that water can only go out,
it really only invalidates this גיסטרא, gistera, this pottery shard. אמר רבי
אתי שונין, amar Rebbi ati shonin, we teach, כלי חרס שיעורו בכינוס
משקה, kli cheres shiuro b'kinus mashkeh,
pottery vessel is the size of a hole that invalidates it is
a hole big enough for water to go in. ולא אמרו מוציא
משקה, v'lo amru motzi mashkeh, so what's the purpose of a hole
that water would only go out? אלא לענין גיסטרא בלבד, ela l'inyan
gistera bilvad, the only time it applies is something that's barely a
vessel to begin with, a pottery shard. מאי טעמא, mai taama, what's
the reason? אמר מר זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן, amar Mar Zutra breih
d'Rav Nachman, לפי שאין אומרים הוי גיסטרא לגיסטרא. lefi she'ein omrim havei
gistera l'gistera. You don't say let's bring a pottery shard to patch
up a pottery shard. Okay, the whole thing is barely a vessel
to begin with, as soon as it's got a problem you throw
it out. Other types of things, they've got a little bit of
a problem, you'll try to fix it, but this thing once it's
got a problem you throw it out so even a tiny little
hole. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, כיצד בודקין
כלי חרס לידע אם ניקב בכינוס משקה אם לאו? keitzad bodkin kli
cheres leida im nikav b'kinus mashkeh im lav? How do you test
to see if whether water can go in or not? Now, you
think it's going to be an easy answer, but let's take a
look at what the גמרא Gemorah says. יביא עריבה מלאה מים, yavi
ariiva mleia mayim, you take a trough like filled with water, you
take a huge vessel filled with water, ונותן קדרה לתוכה, v'nosein kedeira
l'tocha, and you put your push your vessel inside of this other
vessel that's filled with water. אם כנס, im kanas, so if water
goes through the hole at the bottom, בידוע שבכינוס משקה, beyadua sheb'kinus
mashkeh, you know that water can come in. ואם לאו בידוע שמוציא
משקה, v'im lav beyadua shemotzi mashkeh, and if not, then it's big
enough maybe for water to go out, which is easy to test,
but it's not big enough for water to go in. Well, that
seems to be easy enough, but let's see where the גמרא Gemorah
continues, turn the page, מ"ט ע"ב, mem tes amud beis, רבי Rabbi
יהודה Yehuda אומר, omer:
no, כופף אזני קדרה לתוכה ומציף עליה מים.
kofef oznei kedeira l'tocha u'matzif
aleha mayim. No, no, no, you turn a pot inside of a
larger pot, you turn the one with the hole upside down so
that the floor is facing up. ומציף עליה מים, u'matzif aleha mayim,
and then you fill the larger pot with water so that now
water the water level is higher than the floor, the upended floor
of the pot on the inside. ואם כנס, v'im kanas, now if
water gets through that, I guess you would then spill it all
out and look if there was somehow water, you'd flip the whole
thing over and then check inside the lower pot and see if
the inner pot and see if there's water in it. If water
got through that hole, בידוע שבכינוס משקה, beyadua sheb'kinus mashkeh, then it's
big enough for water to go in. ואם לאו בידוע שמוציא משקה,
v'im lav beyadua shemotzi mashkeh, it's big enough for water to go
out but not to go in. What's the purpose of this other
test?
Why doesn't he like the first test? So the answer should be
obvious, because in the first test, you're pushing the pot, the floor
of the pot with a hole down into water, you're creating an
enormous amount of pressure. That pressure is going to cause the water
to come in the hole. That's not the real test. The test
is because that's just like the water in the pot has pressure.
pressure has gravity and pushes into the hole. So what he says
you do is you have to keep the hole up, you have
to turn, invert the pot and float water on top of it.
Then you have a thin layer of water, then you'll see if
water will get in without serious pressure. And that's the test you
have to do. With pressure, it doesn't prove anything. So that's what
ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda says.
Okay, now, oh, here's another test. שפתה על גבי האור, shavta al
gabei ha'or, you put it on top of, you filled up with
water, and there's a fire underneath. אם היא מעמידה, im hi ma'amida,
if the fire prevents water from coming out of the hole, בידוע
שהיא מוציאה משקה, beyaduah shehi motziya mashke, because apparently fire will have
some effect to stop up the hole. So if it does stop
it up, then the water is inside the pot. So when the
water is inside the pot, it should come out more easily. But
encountering that is the fire underneath, which has some effect of stopping
the water from coming out. So if it does stop the water
from coming out, so בידוע שהיא מוציאה משקה, beyaduah shehi motziya mashke,
then the hole's got, then the hole is big enough for water
to come out without a fire, but it's not big enough for
water to go in. מוציא משקה. motzi mashke. Where was I? ואם
לאו, ve'im lav, but if even with the fire water still comes
out, the water on the inside comes out, בידוע שהיא מכניסה משקה,
beyaduah shehi machnisa mashke, then it's a big enough hole that water
would normally come in. So it's an interesting test. You test with
the water on the inside, not the outside, and that by itself
doesn't prove anything, but with the addition of the fire, it says
if even with the fire water will come out from the inside,
then it's a big enough hole that water normally would go in
as well. That's what ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda says. ר' יוסי Reb
Yossi אומר, omer, ר' יוסי Reb Yossi says, אף לא שפתה על
גבי האור, af lo shavta al gabei ha'or, don't do that with
the fire מפני שהיא מעמידה, mipnei shehi ma'amida, the fire will cause
it to stop coming out even if it's a big hole. That
doesn't prove anything because it could be a big hole and with
the fire nothing will come out. אלא שפתה על גבי הרמץ, ela
shavta al gabei ha'remetz, you do it on top of, you use
heat, I agree, but not a live fire. You do it on
top of some like burning embers or like you know whatever, hot
ashes. רמץ מעמידה ובידוע שהיא מוציאה משקה ואם לאו בידוע שהיא מכניסה
משקה, remetz ma'amida uveyaduah shehi motziya mashke ve'im lav beyaduah shehi machnisa
mashke, same point you said, that if the heat stops it from
coming out then it's a tiny hole, if the heat doesn't stop
it from coming out then it's a big enough hole that water
could get in. But I do not use, I would not use
a fire, that wouldn't prove anything, I would use burning ashes.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, היה טוטף? haya totaf? No,
היה טורף טיפה אחר טיפה, haya toreif tipah achar tipah, one final
test, if it's drip drip drip drip drip, so again water's on
the inside, it's not on the outside, but it's such a big
hole that it's constantly dripping out. So that also proves that it's
a big enough hole, בידוע שהיא מכניסה משקה, beyaduah shehi machnisa mashke,
it's big enough for water to come in. So a lot of
different tests, but the big debate was do you can you put
the pot in upside down or right side up. So the גמרא
Gemara says, מאי איכא בין תנא קמא לרבי יהודה, mai ika bein
tanna kamma l'Rabbi Yehuda, what was that debate about whether you put
the pot in floor first or top first. So the גמרא Gemara
says, אמר
עולא כונס על ידי הדחק איכא בינייהו. amar Ulla koness al yedei
ha'dechak ika beineiyahu. The question is if it gets, if water comes
into the hole, but only because of pressure, because you're pushing the
floor into an existing
gathering of
water. So that, does that count like water's coming in? And the
other opinion says no, it has to be able to come in
without pressure. With pressure doesn't prove anything. Okay, so there you have
the different opinions about the size, about
how to test for water coming in. But the basic difference is
that in order to invalidate a vessel, you really need it to
be the size
that water can come in. The one time that the tiny hole
that water goes out is enough is for this thing which is
not really a vessel to begin with. Okay, and now let's see
the next
case. אבר שיש בו ציפורן, eiver sheyeish bo tziporen, a limb with
a fingernail or without. So it says, יש בו ציפורן מטמא במגע
ובמשא ובאוהל, yeish bo tziporen metamei bemaga uvemasa ube'ohel, if it has
a fingernail then it's like a full אבר eiver and אבר מן
החי eiver min hachai or an אבר מן המת, eiver min hamait,
even if it doesn't have enough meat on the bones, you know
whatever, normally you would need a כזית kezayit worth of flesh. But
in this case even if it doesn't, if it's a full אבר,
eiver, then it causes טומאה tuma just like a dead body. Touching,
carrying and even under a tent, you know under a roof. יש
בו עצם ואין בו ציפורן, yeish bo etzem ve'ein bo tziporen, if
it has a bone with no fingernail, so then it does cause
טומאה tuma because there's a bone. If it's אבר מן המת, eiver
min hamait, I'm saying if it's from a dead body, any even
a tiny amount of bone causes טומאה, tuma, but it will not
be enough to cause טומאה tuma in a tent unless you have
either a full limb or you have meat, flesh the amount of
a כזית. kezayit. So in this case where you don't have flesh
the amount of a כזית kezayit and it's not a full limb,
it does not cause טומאה tuma in a tent. So in that
case מטמא במגע ובמשא ואינו מטמא באוהל, metamei bemaga uvemasa ve'eino metamei
be'ohel, touch and carrying
but not underneath a roof. אמר רב חסדא דבר זה רבינו גדול
אמרו המקום יהיה בעזרו, amar Rav Chisda davar zeh rabbeinu gadol amaro
hamakom yihiye be'ezro, this thing our great rabbi taught, God should be
at his side, this is back to רב, Rav, interesting, not רבי,
Rebbi, רב, Rav, this is a way of referring to רב. Rav.
And he just explains the point of our משנה. Mishna. אצבע יתירה
שיש בה עצם ואין בה ציפורן, etzba yeteira sheyeish ba etzem ve'ein
ba tziporen, if it has a bone and no nail, מטמא במגע
ובמשא ואינו מטמא באוהל, metamei bemaga uvemasa ve'eino metamei be'ohel, it causes
טומאה tuma by touch and carrying but not underneath a roof. And
for the reason we said that it's not a full limb and
therefore it does not enough flesh the amount of a כזית. kezayit.
slash and therefore it does not cause טומאה *tumah* under a roof.
אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן *Amar Rabba bar Bar
Chana Amar Rabbi Yochanan*, וכשנספרה אגב היד *vechushenispere agab hayad*. This idea
that it needs to have a fingernail is only when it was
like not lined up with the other fingers, so you would not
count it naturally if you were counting fingers. It’s off on a
different angle. But if it’s lined up with the other fingers, then
even without the fingernail it would count as a limb. So that’s
an interesting additional qualification. Let’s see now to the end of the
משנה *mishna*. כל המטמא מדרס *Kol hametameh midras*, some things can be
a seat without being a... if it’s a seat, it can become
טמא *tamei* from a dead body, but not necessarily vice versa. כל
דחזי למדרס מטמא טמא מת *Kol dechazi lemidras metameh tamei mes*. Anything
fit for being a seat will also become טמא *tamei* from a
dead body. ויש שמטמא טמא מת ואינו מטמא מדרס *Ve’yesh shemetameh tamei
mes ve’eino metameh midras*, something can be טמא *tamei* from a dead
body but not fit for being a seat. לאתויי מאי *Le’asuyei mai*?
What does this include? לאתויי סאה ותרקב *Le’asuyei sa’ah ve’tirkav*, like these
big types of things that are used for like measuring wheat, like
these big, you know, buckets that are different measurements for wheat. Those
types of things, דתניא *detanya*, הישב על הכלי *hayoshev al hakeli*, if
you sit on a vessel you make it a מדרס *midras*, you
make it an אב הטומאה *av hatumah* if it's a זב *zav*
or זבה *zavah*. יכול כפה סאה וישב עליה ותרקב וישב עליה יהא
טמא *Yachol kafa sa’ah ve’yashav aleha ve’tirkav ve’yashav aleha yehei tamei*, maybe
if you took a big measuring, you know, box for wheat and
you flipped it over and you sat on it, it would become
considered a seat of a זב *zav* or זבה *zavah* and it
would be an אב הטומאה *av hatumah*. תלמוד לומר *Talmud lomar*, אשר
ישב עליו *asher yeshav alav*, that you will regularly sit on it
is how it's read. הזב *Hazav*, ממי שיחד לישיבה *mimi sheyuchad liyeshiva*,
something that is regularly sat on. יצא זו *Yatza zu*, to exclude
this case, שאומרים לו עמד ונעשה מלאכתנו *she’omrim lo amad ve’na’aseh melachtenu*,
hey buddy, get off, we need to use that to measure our
wheat. So something that you cannot even if you wanted to designate
for a seat, it might be able to function as it, but
you’re not going to be able to designate as a seat because
people are going to want to take it away and use it
for its more primary purpose. That type of a thing will never
be considered a משכב ומושב *mishkav u’moshav* of a זב *zav* and
זבה *zavah*, but obviously will become טמא *tameh* from a dead body.
It could have given an easier example like I said, like a
pin, but this was a more interesting example because this is something
that can function as a seat but because it can never be
its primary function, it does not become טמא *tameh* as a משכב
ומושב *mishkav u’moshav*. Okay, so let’s just, I know we’re going a
little quick today, but it’s a pretty straightforward גמרא *Gemara*. Let’s just
read the next משנה *mishna* and then we’re going to have to
end in the next three or four minutes. Okay, so כל הראוי
לדון דיני נפשות ראוי לדון דיני ממונות *Kol hara’uy ladun dinei nefashot
ra’uy ladun dinei mamonot*. This is going to actually be probably could
engender a lot of conversation, but we won't be have that now.
Anybody that can be a judge for capital cases can be a
judge for monetary cases. ויש שראוי לדון דיני ממונות ואינו ראוי לדון
דיני נפשות *Ve’yesh shera’uy ladun dinei mamonot ve’eino ra’uy ladun dinei nefashot*.
Some can be monetary but not capital on cases. גמרא *Gemara*, אמר
רב יהודה *Amar Rav Yehuda*, לאתויי מאי *Le’asuyei mai*? לאתויי ממזר *Le’asuyei
mamzer*. What one of a difference would be a ממזר *mamzer*, somebody
who obviously is born from an incestuous union? In that type of
a case, although on the one hand the גמרא *Gemara* at the
end of הוריות *Horayot*, the משנה *mishna* says if a ממזר תלמיד
חכם *mamzer talmid chacham* comes before a כהן גדול עם הארץ *kohen
gadol am ha’aretz*, you know, in certain hierarchies that’s completely irrelevant. It’s
all about, you know, especially after the Temple it was all about,
you know, the Torah knowledge that you have and so on, and
these issues of יחוס *yichus* were not relevant. Nevertheless, in other areas
the issue of יחוס *yichus* is very relevant and one of them
is about this case of who sits on a capital on a
court for capital crimes, and somebody that is a ממזר *mamzer* that
has this, you know, this problematic heritage, not heritage, you know, sort
of what’s it called, יחוס *yichus*, ancestry, whatever, you know what I’m
saying, יחוס *yichus*, anyway, is not fit for sitting on a on
such a court. תנינא חדא זימנא *Tanina chada zimna*. So גמרא *Gemara*
says but we already talked about that. We talk כל הכשר לדון
בסנהדרין דיני ממונות אינו כל הכשר לדון דיני נפשות *Kol hakesher ladun
be’Sanhedrin dinei mamonot eino kol hakesher ladun dinei nefashot*. Anybody can be
on a civil court, not everybody can be on a capital crime.
והוינא בה *Vahavina bah*, we said לאתויי מאי *Le’asuyei mai*, what’s an
example? ואמר רב יהודה לאתויי ממזר *Ve’amar Rav Yehuda le’asuyei mamzer*, and
he said there also ממזר *mamzer* was an example. So what’s the
purpose of saying it twice? So גמרא *Gemara* says alright, חדא לאתויי
גר וחדא לאתויי ממזר *chada le’asuyei ger ve’chada le’asuyei mamzer*. They’re not
both excluding a ממזר *mamzer*, one’s excluding a ממזר *mamzer* and the
other is excluding a גר *ger*. So this again, very you know,
disturbing גמרות *Gemaros* for our sort of more, you know, democratic egalitarian
sense here that why should any of this matter in terms of
somebody’s being fit for you know for this type of a position.
And let’s just see what how the גמרא *Gemara* ends here. It
says וצריכי *Vetzrichi*, you need both. דאי אשמעינן גר משום דראוי לבוא
בקהל *De’ei ashme’inan ger mishum dera’uy lavo be’kahal*, if it said a
גר *ger* because at least he has no restrictions of marrying. אבל
ממזר דאין ראוי לבוא בקהל *Aval mamzer de’ein ra’uy lavo be’kahal*, a
ממזר *mamzer* cannot marry in, אימא לא *eima lo*, maybe he’s considered
more on the outside of the community maybe or more stigmatized and
therefore not fit for this role. ואי אשמעינן ממזר *Ve’ei ashme’inan mamzer*,
if it said a ממזר *mamzer*, משום דקאתי מטיפה כשרה *mishum dekasi
mitipa keshera*, at least he’s coming from you know, he’s born, conceived
by Jews even though in sin, but conceived by Jews. אבל גר
דקאתי מטיפה פסולה *Aval ger dekasi mitipa pesula*, but a גר *ger*
that came from a non-Jewish heritage, אימא לא *eima lo*, maybe he
also is somehow more excluded. צריכא *Tzericha*, so we can now rest
assured that both of them are excluded.
Not necessarily the greatest גמרא to end on because it obviously is
deeply problematic, I think, for a sense of, you know, of our
more sort of democratic egalitarian senses and understanding why that should exclude
somebody from playing these roles is not at all clear, so I
will leave you all of that for food for thought and if
you want to we can pick up with that tomorrow. Okay? So
בוקר טוב boker tov everybody, we're going to end here, okay? Make
sure and be well. Okay, bye.